Election night 2008
ليلة نتائج إنتخابات ٢٠٠٨
was a night that tore me in half.
كانت ليلة قسمتني إلى نصفين
It was the night that Barack Obama was elected.
كانت هذه الليلة التي أنتخب فيها باراك اوباما رئيساً
[One hundred and forty-three] years after the end of slavery,
١٤٣ عاماً بعد إنتهاء عصر العبودية
and [43] years after the passage
و٤٨ عاماً بعد قبول
of the Voting Rights Act,
قانون حقوق التصويت.
an African-American was elected president.
تم انتخاب رئيس لأمريكا من اصول إفريقية
Many of us never thought that this was possible
كثر منا لم يتوقّعوا أن يحدث هذا
until the moment that it happened.
إلا عندما حدث فعلا
And in many ways, it was the climax
وبطرق كثيرة، كانت هذه النقطة الفاصلة
of the black civil rights movement
في تاريخ حركة الحقوق المدنية للسود
in the United States.
في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية.
I was in California that night,
ليلتها، كنت في كاليفورنيا
which was ground zero at the time
التي كانت انذاك نقطة الصفر
for another movement:
لحركةٍ أخرى
the marriage equality movement.
حركة مساواة الزواج.
Gay marriage was on the ballot
كان زواج المثليين على ورقة الإقتراع
in the form of Proposition 8,
في شكل المقترح ٨
and as the election returns started to come in,
و مع بدء وصول نتائج الانتخابات
it became clear that the right
بدى واضحا أنّ حق
for same sex couples to marry,
الزواج لأبناء الجنس الواحد
which had recently been granted by the California courts,
الذي كان قد ضمن من قبل محاكم كاليفورنيا
was going to be taken away.
سيسلب.
So on the same night
ففي نفس الليلة التي
that Barack Obama won his historic presidency,
فاز باراك اوباما بمنصبه التاريخي
the lesbian and gay community suffered
عانى مجتمع المثليين
one of our most painful defeats.
واحدة من أكبر خيبات الامل
And then it got even worse.
و بدأ الأمر يسوء.
Pretty much immediately,
مباشرةً بعد ذلك
African-Americans started to be blamed
الامريكيين السود بدأوا يلامو
for the passage of Proposition 8.
على قَبول اطروحة ٨
This was largely due to an incorrect poll that said
كان هذا بسبب نتائج استطلاع خاطئ
that blacks had voted for the measure
استطلع بأن أصوات السود للأطروحة
by something like 70 percent.
كانت تعد قرابة ٧٠٪
This turned out not to be true,
أكتشف ان هذا كان خطأ،
but this idea of pervasive black homophobia set in,
ولكن فكرة اتصال رهاب المثلية بالسود
and was grabbed on by the media.
كان الاعلام فد بدأ بإجتذاب الناس بها
I couldn't tear myself away from the coverage.
لم استطع ان أبعد انظاري عن هذه التغطية.
I listened to some gay commentator say
سمعت معلّقا مثليا يقول
that the African-American community
أنّ المجتمع الأمريكيين الأفارقة
was notoriously homophobic,
يتسم معظمه بالرهاب المثلي
and now that civil rights had been achieved for us,
و الآن بما أن حركة الحقوق المدنية قد حققت من أجلنا
we wanted to take away other people's rights.
أصبحنا نريد أن نسلب حقوق أناس آخرين
There were even reports of racist epithets
كان هنالك تقارير عن صدور صفات عنصرية
being thrown at some of the participants
تمّ نعت بعض المشاركين بها
of the gay rights rallies
في إحدى المسيرات المخصصة لحقوق المثليين
that took place after the election.
التي كانت تحدث بعد الانتخابات.
And on the other side,
و من الجهة الأخرى،
some African-Americans dismissed or ignored
بعض الأمريكيين الأفارقة كانوا يتغاضون عن
homophobia that was indeed real in our community.
ظاهرة كره المثليين التي كانت شائعة في مجتمعنا.
And others resented this comparison
أناس كثر كرهوا المقارنة
between gay rights and civil rights,
بين حقوق المثليّين و الحقوق المدنية
and once again, the sinking feeling
و مرة أخرى عم الإحساس الموجع
that two minority groups
أنّ مجموعتين من الأقلية
of which I'm both a part of
و التي كنت أنا أنتمي إليها الاثنين
were competing with each other
تنافسان بعضهما البعض
instead of supporting each other
بدلاً من التضامن سوياً
overwhelmed and, frankly, pissed me off.
أصبح يشعرني بالغضب
Now, I'm a documentary filmmaker,
الآن أنا صانعة أفلام وثائقية
so after going through my pissed off stage
بعد أن مرَّت فترة الغضب
and yelling at the television and radio,
والصياح على شاشة التلفاز
my next instinct was
وجهتني غرائزي إلى أن
to make a movie.
أصنع فيلماً
And what guided me in making this film was,
وكات الأفكار التي تصاحبني دوماً
how was this happening?
كيف يحدث كل هذا؟
How was it that the gay rights movement
كيف يتم تحريض حركة حقوق المثليّين
was being pitted against the civil rights movement?
ضد حركة الحقوق المدنية؟
And this wasn't just an abstract question.
لم تكن هذه أسئلة عامة.
I'm a beneficiary of both movements,
أنا من المستفيدين من كلتا الحركتين
so this was actually personal.
فأصبحت المسألة شخصية.
But then something else happened
ولكن حدث شيء آخر
after that election in 2008.
بعد انتخابات ٢٠٠٨ .
The march towards gay equality
المضي نحو منع حقوق للمثليّين
accelerated at a pace
بدأ يتسارع في وتيرته
that surprised and shocked everyone,
وكان هذا مصدر صدمة للجميع
and is still reshaping our laws and our policies,
و لا يزال يعيد هيكلة قوانيننا و أحكامنا
our institutions and our entire country.
و منشئاتنا و وطننا كله.
And so it started to become increasingly clear to me
لقد بدأت الصورة تتّضح لي
that this pitting of the two movements
أنّ هذا التحريض للحركتين
against each other actually didn't make sense,
ضد بعضهما البعض لم يكن عقلانياً
and that they were in fact
و أنهما كانتا في الواقع
much, much more interconnected,
متصلتين أكثر بكثير
and that, in fact, some of the way
و أنه في الواقع، بطريقة ما
that the gay rights movement has been able
أصبح لحركة حقوق المثليّين القدرة على أن
to make such incredible gains so quickly
تحصد ثمارا كثيرة سريعاً
is that it's used some of the same tactics
بسبب إتباعها نفس المنهج
and strategies that were first laid down
و الطريقة التي وضعتها
by the civil rights movement.
حركة الحقوق المدنية.
Let's just look at a few of these strategies.
دعونا ننظر لهذا المنهج عن كثب
First off, it's really interesting to see,
أولاً، من المثير للاهتمام أن ترى
to actually visually see, how quick
مدى سرعة
the gay rights movement has made its gains,
التحقيقات في حركة حقوق المثليّين
if you look at a few of the major events
إذا نظرت إلى بعض الأهداف الرئيسية
on a timeline of both freedom movements.
التي حدثت في تاريخ حركتي التحرير هاتين .
Now, there are tons of milestones
الآن هنالك الكثير من المراحل
in the civil rights movement,
في حركة التحرير المدنية
but the first one we're going to start with
ولكن أولها بدأت بمقاطعة الحافلة
is the 1955 Montgomery bus boycott.
في "مونتجمري" عام ١٩٥٥
This was a protest campaign
كانت هذه حملة احتجاجية
against Montgomery, Alabama's segregation
ضد التفرقة العنصرية في مونتجومري آلاباما
on their public transit system,
في منظومة النقل العام الخاصة بالولاية
and it began when a woman named Rosa Parks
و بدأ هذا من قبل إمرأة إسمها "روزا باركس"
refused to give up her seat to a white person.
التي رفضت أن تتخلى عن مقعدها لشخص أبيض
The campaign lasted a year,
الحملة دامت سنة
and it galvanized the civil rights movement
و قوّت حركة الحقوق المدنية
like nothing had before it.
كما لم يحدث من قبل.
And I call this strategy the
و أطلق على هذه الإستراتيجية
"I'm tired of your foot on my neck" strategy.
استراتيجية "لقد تعبت من قدمك التي فوق عنقي".
So gays and lesbians have been in society
المثليون جنسياً موجودون في مجتمعنا
since societies began,
منذ قديم الأزل،
but up until the mid-20th century,
و لكن حتى نصف القرن العشرين
homosexual acts were still illegal in most states.
ظلت منافية للقوانين في معظم الولايات.
So just 14 years after the Montgomery bus boycott,
بعد ١٤ عاماً من مقاطعة باص مونتجومري
a group of LGBT folks took that same strategy.
اتبعت مجموعة من مناهضي حقوق المثلية نفس الإسترايجية
It's known as Stonewall, in 1969,
عرفت ب"ستونوال" في ١٩٦٩
and it's where a group of LGBT patrons
وفيها ردعت مجموعة من المثليّين
fought back against police beatings
عنف الشرطة
at a Greenwich Village bar that sparked
في حانة "جرين ڤيلاج" و سبّب هذا
three days of rioting.
ثلاثة أيام من التظاهر.
Incidentally, black and latino LGBT folks
و بالصدفة، كان السود واللاتينيون المثليون
were at the forefront of this rebellion,
في الصفوف الأولى في المقاومة
and it's a really interesting example
و هذا متال مذهل عن
of the intersection of our struggles against racism,
ترابط الصراع ضد العنصرية والرهاب
homophobia, gender identity and police brutality.
المثليّ و الهوية الجنسية و عنف قوات الأمن.
After Stonewall happened, gay liberation groups
بعد حدوث "ستونوال" تكاثرت مجموعات
sprang up all over the country,
الدفاع عن حقوق المثليين بالبلد.
and the modern gay rights movement as we know it took off.
و بدأت الحركة لتصل لما نحن عليه اليوم
So the next moment to look at on the timeline
اللحظة التالية في طريق التحرير كانت
is the 1963 March on Washington.
في عام ١٩٦٣ في مسيرة واشنتون
This was a seminal event in the civil rights movement
التي كانت مصيرية في حركة الحقوق المدنية
and it's where African-Americans called for both
و فيها نادى الأمريكان الأفارقة
civil and economic justice.
بالعدل المدني و المادي.
And it's of course where Martin Luther King
كان هذا بالطبع حيث ألقى "مارتن لوثر كينغ"
delivered his famous "I have a dream" speech,
خطابه الشهير "عندي حلم"
but what's actually less known
و ما لا يعرفه الكثيرون
is that this march was organized
هو أنّ هذه المسيرة نظمت
by a man named Bayard Rustin.
من قبل رجل يدعى "بايارد روستين".
Bayard was an out gay man,
بايارد كان رجل معترفاً بمثليّته
and he's considered one of the most brilliant
و يعتبر أحد ألمع
strategists of the civil rights movement.
الاستراتيجيين في حركة الحقوق المدنية.
He later in his life became a fierce advocate
لاحقاً أصبح مناهضاً قوياً
of LGBT rights as well, and his life
لحقوق المثليّين، و سرعان ما
is testament to the intersection of the struggles.
أصبح رمزاً لإجتماع الصراعين.
The March on Washington
مسيرة واشنطون هي
is one of the high points of the movement,
إحدى أهم مراحل الحركة،
and it's where there was a fervent belief
و من هنا ظهر الإقتناع العتيد
that African-Americans too
بأن الأمريكان الأفارقة أيضاً لهم الحق
could be a part of American democracy.
في الانتفاع بالديمقراطية الأمريكية.
I call this strategy the
أطلق على هذه الإستراتيجية
"We are visible and many in numbers" strategy.
"نحن ظاهرون و كثيرون بأعدادنا".
Some early gay activists were actually
في الواقع، بضع من النشطاء المثلّيين
directly inspired by the march,
جائهم الإلهام بسبب المسيرة
and some had taken part.
و بعضهم كان قد شارك فيها.
Gay pioneer Jack Nichols said,
المثلي الرائد "جاك نيكولز" قال
"We marched with Martin Luther King,
"سرنا مع مارتن لوثر كينغ،
seven of us from the Mattachine Society" --
سبعةٌ منا من مجتمع "ماتاشين""
which was an early gay rights organization —
الذي كان من أوائل مجتمعات حقوق المثليّين
"and from that moment on, we had our own dream
"و منذ ذلك، أصبح لدينا حلم
about a gay rights march of similar proportions."
بخصوص مسيرة مشابهة لحقوق المثليّين."
Several years later, a series of marches took place,
و بعد بضع سنوات، حدثت سلسلة من المسيرات،
each one gaining the momentum
و مع كل واحدة منهن زادت
of the gay freedom struggle.
مجهودات الصراع لحقوق الحرية.
The first one was in 1979,
أولهن كانت في ١٩٧٩،
and the second one took place in 1987.
و الثانية كانت في ١٩٨٧.
The third one was held in 1993.
أما الثالثة كانت في ١٩٩٣.
Almost a million people showed up,
قرابة المليون شخص شارك،
and people were so energized and excited
كانوا نشطاء و متحمسين
by what had taken place,
بسبب ما كان يحدث،
they went back to their own communities
و عادوا لمجتمعاتهم
and started their own political
و بدأو منظماتهم
and social organizations,
السياسية و الإجتماعية،
further increasing the visibility of the movement.
ممّا ساهم في كثرة ظهور الحركة.
The day of that march, October 11,
يوم المسيرة الموافق ١١ أكتوبر
was then declared National Coming Out Day,
تم إعلانه يوم الإعتراف بالمثلية الوطني،
and is still celebrated all over the world.
و لا يزال يحتفل به في جميع أنحاء العالم.
These marches set the groundwork
هذه المسيرات كانت حجر الأساس
for the historic changes that we see happening
للتغييرات التاريخية التي نراها تحدث
today in the United States.
اليوم في الولايات المتحدة.
And lastly, the "Loving" strategy.
و أخيراً، تأتي إستراتيجية " المحبة".
The name speaks for itself.
إن الإسم يتحدث عن نفسه.
In 1967, the Supreme Court ruled
في عام ١٩٦٧، حكمت المحكمة العليا
in Loving v. Virginia,
في حكم "لوڤينغ ڤيرجينيا"
and invalidated all laws
و أنهت صلاحية كل القوانين
that prohibited interracial marriage.
التي منعت زواج البيض بالسود.
This is considered one of the Supreme Court's
يعد هذا الحكم أحد أهم القرارات التي إتخذتها
landmark civil rights cases.
المحكمة العليا في قضايا الحقوق المدنية.
In 1996, President Clinton signed
في ١٩٩٦، وقّع الرئيس كلينتون
the Defense of Marriage Act, known as DOMA,
مرسوم الدفاع عن الزواج المعروف ب "دوما"،
and that made the federal government
جعل هذا الحكومة الفدرالية
only have to recognize marriages
تعترف بالزواج
between a man and a woman.
بين رجلٍ و إمرأة فقط.
In United States v. Windsor,
في قرار "الولايات المتحدة ويندزور"
a 79-year-old lesbian named Edith Windsor
إمرأة مثلية عمرها ٧٩ عاماً تدعى "إيديث ويندسور"
sued the federal government
قاضت الحكومة الفدرالية
when she was forced to pay estate taxes
عندما أجبرت على دفع ضرائب ملكية
on her deceased wife's property,
عن ملكية زوجتها المتوفاه.
something that heterosexual couples don't have to do.
شيء لا يفعله الأزواج غير المثليين.
And as the case wound its way
و بينما كانت القضية تسلك مسلكها
through the lower courts,
في المحاكم السفلية
the Loving case was repeatedly cited as precedent.
كانت قضية "لوڤينج" تستخدم كمثال أسبق.
When it got to the Supreme Court in 2013,
عندما وصلت للمحكمة العليا في عام ٢٠١٣،
the Supreme Court agreed,
حكمت المحكمة العليا إجماعاً،
and DOMA was thrown out.
و تم إلغاء "دوما".
It was incredible.
كان الأمر مذهلاً.
But the gay marriage movement
لكن حركة زواج المثليّين
has been making gains for years now.
كانت تجني نتائجها في الآونة الأخيرة.
To date, 17 states
حتى اليوم، ١٧ ولاية
have passed laws allowing marriage equality.
أصدرت قوانين موافقة على زواج المثليية.
It's become the de facto battle
أصبحت معركة واقعية
for gay equality,
لحصول المثليّين على المساواة،
and it seems like daily,
و يبدو أنّه يوميا
laws prohibiting it are being challenged in the courts,
قوانين التحريم تمر بصعوبات في المحاكم
even in places like Texas and Utah,
حتى في أماكن مثل "يوتاه" و "تيكساس"،
which no one saw coming.
التي لم يكن أحد يتوقّع أن يحدث ذلك هناك.
So a lot has changed
إذاً، تغير الكثير
since that night in 2008
منذ تلك الليلة في ٢٠٠٨
when I felt torn in half.
عندما شعرت أنني مقسمة نصفين.
I did go on to make that film.
فعلاً خرجت و صنعت ذلك الفيلم.
It's a documentary film,
إنه فيلم وثائقي،
and it's called "The New Black,"
و يدعى "الأسود الجديد"،
and it looks at how the African-American community
و ينظر إلى صراع المجتمع الأسود
is grappling with the gay rights issue
مع أزمة حقوق المثليّين
in light of the gay marriage movement
في ضوء حركة تزووج المثليّين
and this fight over the meaning of civil rights.
و هذا الصراع حول معنى الحقوق المدنية.
And I wanted to capture
و أردت أن ألتقط بعض التغييرات
some of this incredible change that was happening,
الجذرية التي كانت تحدث،
and as luck or politics would have it,
و بفضل الحظ و السياسة،
another marriage battle started gearing up,
بدأ صراع آخر في قضية الزواج.
this time in Maryland,
هذه المرة في "ماريلاند"
where African-Americans make up 30 percent
حيث السود يشكّلون ٣٠٪
of the electorate.
من الناخبين.
So this tension between gay rights
فذاك الصراع بين حقوق المثليّين
and civil rights started to bubble up once again,
والحقوق المدنية بدأ أن يظهر مرة خرى،
and I was lucky enough to capture
و كنت محظوظة كفاية لتمكّني من إلتقاط
how some people were making the connection
كيف كان الناس يقومون بنوع من الوصل
between the movements this time.
ما بين الحركتين.
This is a clip of Karess Taylor-Hughes
هذا مقطع فيه "كاريس تيلور هيوز"
and Samantha Masters, two characters in the film,
و "سامانثا ماسترز"، شخصيتان في الفيلم،
as they hit the streets of Baltimore
و هما تسلكان شوارع "بالتيمور"
and try to convince potential voters.
و تحاولان أن تقنعا ناخبين محتملين.
(Video) Samantha Masters: That's what's up, man, this is a righteous man over here.
(الڤيديو) سامانثا ماستر(س.م): هذا رجل محترم هنا.
Okay, are you registered to vote?
حسناً، هل أنت من الناخبين؟
Man: No. Karess Taylor-Hughes: Okay. How old are you?
الرجل: لا. كاريس تيلور هيوز(ك.ت.ه): ما هو سنك؟
Man: 21. KTH: 21? You gotta get registered to vote.
الرجل: ٢١.
We got to get you registered to vote.
(ك.ت.ه): ٢١؟ يجب أن تسجل إسمك!
Man: I ain't voting on no gay shit.
الرجل: لن أصوت لأي شيء عن المثليّين.
SM: Okay, why? What's up? Man: I ain't with that.
(س.م): لماذا؟ الرجل: لست مع هذا.
SM: That's not cool.
(س.م): هذا ليس أمرا جيد.
Man: What made you be gay? SM: So what made you be straight?
الرجل: ما الذي جعلك مثليّة؟
So what made you be straight?
(س.م): ما الذي جعلك مغايرا؟
Man 2: You can't answer that question. (Laughter)
الرجل ٢: ليس بإستطاعتك أن تجاوب على هذا السؤال. (ضحك)
KSM: I used to not have the same rights as you,
(ك.ت.ه): لم يكن لدي مثل حقوقك
but I know that because a black man like yourself
و لكني أعرف ذلك لأن رجلا أسود مثلك
stood up for a woman like me,
وقف في صف إمرأةٍ مثلي،
I know that I've got the same opportunities.
فإني أعلم أن لدي نفس الفرص.
So you, as a black man, have the opportunity
لذا، فبكونك رجلا أسود لديك الفرصة
to stand up for somebody else.
لأن تقف في صالح شخص آخر.
Whether you're gay or not,
إذا ما كنت مثليّا أم لا،
these are your brothers and sisters out here,
فإن هؤلاء إخوتك و أخواتك هنا،
and they need you to represent.
ويحتاجون صوتك.
Man 2: Who is you to tell somebody
الرجل٢: من انت لتقولين لشخص ما
who they can't have sex with,
الذين لايستطيعون ممارسة الجنس معه,
who they can't be with?
من يستطيع أن يعيش معه؟
They ain't got that power.
ليس لديهم هذه السلطة.
Nobody has that power to say, you can't marry that young lady.
لا يملك أحد السلطة أن يقول ليس بإستطاعتك
Who has that power? Nobody.
الزواج من هذه أو ذاك. لا أحد.
SM: But you know what?
(س.م):و لكن تعلم ماذا؟
Our state has put the power in your hands,
ولايتنا قد وضعت
and so what we need you to do
هذا الحق لديك. و نحن في حاجة لك
is vote for, you gonna vote for 6.
أن تصوت، أن تصوت للرقم ٦.
Man 2: I got you.
الرجل ٢: أنا معكم.
SM: Vote for 6, okay?
(س.م): صوتوا ل٦! الرجل٢: أنا معكم
KSM: All right, do y'all need community service hours?
(ك.ت.ه): هل تحتاجون لساعات خدمة إجتماعية؟
You do? All right, you can always volunteer with us
تحتاجون؟ يمكنكم أن تتطوعوا معنا
to get community service hours.
حتى تحصلوا على الساعات.
Y'all want to do that?
تريدون أن تفعلوا هذا؟
We feed you. We bring you pizza.
سوف نطعمكم، نطعكم البيتزا.
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
Yoruba Richen: Thank you.
يوريوبا: شكراً.
What's amazing to me about that clip
المذهل في هذا المقطع هو
that we just captured as we were filming
او نحن نلتقط، ظهر أن
is, it really shows how Karess
كاريس كانت
understands the history of the civil rights movement,
تفهم تاريخ حركة الحقوق المدنية
but she's not restricted by it.
و لكنها لم تكن مقيدة بها.
She doesn't just limit it to black people.
إنها لا تجعلها تقتصر فقط على السود.
She sees it as a blueprint
فإنها تراها و كأنها مخطوطة
for expanding rights to gays and lesbians.
لتوسع حقوق المثليّين.
Maybe because she's younger, she's like 25,
ربما لأنها أصغر فهي تبلغ ٢٥ عاماً
she's able to do this a little bit more easily,
فلديها القدرة على أن تفعل هذا بطريقة أسهل،
but the fact is that Maryland voters
و لكن في الواقع الكثير صوت في "ماريلاند"
did pass that marriage equality amendment,
و بالفعل نجحوا في إصدار التعديل لمساواة حقوق الزواج
and in fact it was the first time
و لأول مرة بالفعل تم
that marriage equality was directly voted on
التصويت على حق مساواة الزواج
and passed by the voters.
من قبل المصوتين نفسهم.
African-Americans supported it at a higher level
الأمريكان الأفارقة صوتوا بنسب
than had ever been recorded.
أعلى من أي وقت مضى.
It was a complete turnaround from that night
كان الأمر بمثابة تيار عكسي
in 2008 when Proposition 8 was passed.
منذ تلك الليلة في ٢٠٠٨ حينما قبل اقتراح ٨.
It was, and feels, monumental.
كان و لا يزال شعورا رائعا.
We in the LGBT community have gone
فنحن المثليّون انتقلنا
from being a pathologized and reviled
من كوننا مرضى و ملعونين
and criminalized group
و مجموعة إجرامية
to being seen as part of the great human quest
إلى أن أصبحنا نُرى كجزء من أعظم
for dignity and equality.
الإنتصارات الإنسانية للكرامة و المساواة.
We've gone from having to hide our sexuality
أصبحنا لا نخبئ هويتنا الجنسية
in order to maintain our jobs and our families
حتى نحافظ على أعمالنا و عائلاتنا
to literally getting a place at the table
و أصبحنا نجلس على نفس الطاولة
with the president
مع الرئيس
and a shout out at his second inauguration.
واعترافه في خطابه الرئاسي الثاني.
I just want to read what he said
أريد أن اقرأ عليكم ما قال
at that inauguration:
في ذاك الخطاب:
"We the people declare today
"نحن الشعب نقر اليوم
that the most evident of truths,
بأن أكثر الحقائق وضوحاً هو
that all of us are created equal.
أنّا خُلقنا كلّنا سواسية.
It is the star that guides us still,
فإنها النجمة التي تظل ترشدنا
just as it guided our forebears
كما أرشدت الذين سبقونا
through Seneca Falls
إلى "سينيكا فولز"
and Selma and Stonewall."
و "سيلما" و "ستونوول".
Now we know that everything is not perfect,
الآن نحن على علم بأن كل شيء ليس كامل
especially when you look at what's happening
بالأخص بالنظر للأمور الراهنة
with the LGBT rights issue internationally,
مع المثليّين في مختلف أنحاء العالم،
but it says something about how far we've come
و لكنه دلالة على الشوط الذي قطعناه
when our president puts the gay freedom struggle
عندما يضع الرئيس نضال المثليين للحرية
in the context of the other great freedom struggles
مع صراعات الحرية العظيمة الأخرى
of our time: the women's rights movement
التي حدثت في زماننا مثل حركة حرية المرأة
and the civil rights movement.
و حركة الحقوق المدنية.
His statement demonstrates not only
فكلماته تدل ليس فقط على
the interconnectedness of those movements,
تلاحم الحركات
but how each one borrowed
و لكن عن كيفية استعارة كلّ منها
and was inspired by the other.
و تأثرت بالأخرى.
So just as Martin Luther King
إذاً فمثلما فعل "مارتن لوثر كينغ"
learned from and borrowed from Gandhi's tactics
حيث تعلم من طرق "غاندي"
of civil disobedience and nonviolence,
في العصيان المدني و السلمية،
which became a bedrock of the civil rights movement,
الذان أصبحتا أساساً لحركة الحقوق المدنية،
the gay rights movement saw what worked
حركة حقوق المثليّين رأت ما نَفِع
in the civil rights movement,
في حركة الحقوق المدنية
and they used some of those same strategies
وإستخدموا بعض هذه الإستراتيجيات
and tactics to make gains
و التنظيمات ليجنوا الثمار
at an even quicker pace.
بطريقة أسرع.
Maybe one more other reason
ربما كان هذا سببا آخر
for the relative quick progress
للسرعة النسبية لما كان يحدث
of the gay rights movement.
في حركة حقوق المثليّين
Whereas a lot of us continue to still live
بينما كثير منا نعيش في
in racially segregated spaces,
أماكن تحتوي تفرقة عنصرية
LGBT folks, we are everywhere.
نحن المثليّون في كل مكان.
We are in urban communities
إننا في المناطق المتحضرة
and rural communities,
وفي المناطق النائية
communities of color, immigrant communities,
وفي المجتمعات متعددة العرق
churches and mosques and synagogues.
و المجتمعات المهاجرة و الكنائس والمساجد و المعابد.
We are your mothers and brothers
نحن أمهاتكم و إخوتكم
and sisters and sons.
و أخواتكم و أبنائكم.
And when someone that you love
و حينما يكون شخص تحبونه
or a family member comes out,
أو فرد من عائلتكم يعترف بمثليته
it may be easier to support their quest for equality.
يمكن أن يكون تشجيعكم للمساواة أسهل.
And in fact, the gay rights movement
و في الواقع حركة حقوق المثليّين
asks us to support justice and equality
تتطلب تشجيع العدل و المساواة
from a space of love.
عن طريق الحب.
That may be the biggest, greatest gift
قد تكون هذه أعظم هدية
that the movement has given us.
أهدتنا إياها هذه الحركة.
It calls on us to access that which is most universal
فإنها تنادينا لأن نتواصل مع
and most intimate:
شيء حميم جداً
a love of our brother and our sister
كحبنا لإخوتنا و أخواتنا
and our neighbor.
و جارنا.
I just want to end with a quote
أريد أن أنهي بمقولة
by one of our greatest freedom fighters
قالها أحد أعظم محاربي الحرية
who's no longer with us, Nelson Mandela
الذي توفيّ، و هو نيلسون مانديلا
of South Africa.
من جنوب أفريقيا.
Nelson Mandela led South Africa
قاد مانديلا جنوب أفريقيا
after the dark and brutal days of Apartheid,
بعد ظلمة و قسوة ال"أبارتايد"
and out of the ashes of that legalized racial discrimination,
و أخرجها من رماد التفرقة القانونية
he led South Africa to become the first country
و قاد جنوب أفريقيا لأن تكون أول بلد
in the world to ban discrimination
في العالم تمنع التفرقة
based on sexual orientation within its constitution.
على أساس التوجه الجنسي في دستورها.
Mandela said,
مانديلا قال،
"For to be free is not merely to cast off one's chains,
"حتى يكون المرء حرّا، لا يجب التخلص من القيد،
but to live in a way that respects
بل العيش بطريقة تحترم
and enhances the freedom of others."
و تحسن فرص حرية الآخرين."
So as these movements continue on,
فإذاً طالما هذه الحركات ستستمر،
and as freedom struggles around the world continue on,
و الصراع نحو الحرية مستمر في جميع أنحاء العالم،
let's remember that not only are they interconnected,
فلنتذكر أنهم ليسو فقط متصلين،
but they must support and enhance each other
و لكنهم يزيدون و يحسنون بعضهم البعض
for us to be truly victorious.
حتى نصير فعلياً منتصرين.
Thank you.
شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)